How did the War of 1812 actually happen?
Why did Britain invade the United States
again less than 30 years after losing
the colonies? How close did the Young
Republic come to disaster? From defeat
on the Northern Frontier to the burning
of the White House, and how did a war
that began in chaos end with one of the
most dramatic American victories of the
age? To understand all of that, from how
Britain and the United States went to
war again to the most important battles
of the conflict, we have to go back to
the very beginning.
The causes of the war were rooted in
trade. In 1807, the British passed the
orders in council that called for
American ships to be blocked from
trading with France. The British had
also taken to capturing American ships
and forcing their sailors into service
in the Royal Navy. Britain was at war
with Napoleon at the time and needed the
manpower. America made numerous appeals
to Britain to change its policies, but
was ignored. The French in turn were
doing the same thing, seizing American
ships, blocking them from British ports,
and forcing American sailors into
service in the French Navy.
The actions of both countries were
aggravating, but America realized it
could play the two rivals off each
other. In May 1810, Makin's bill called
for free and open trade with both
countries despite their offenses, but
with a catch. Madison would immediately
suspend all American trade with one
power if the other lifted all their
restrictions on American trade.
Basically, he counted on Britain and
France wanting to harm each other more
than wanting to restrict Americans.
Napoleon left at the chance first and
made promises of lifting the
restrictions, but demanded that Madison
embargo Britain immediately. Madison was
happy with the offer and announced his
intention to do exactly that. But it
didn't take long for him to realize
Napoleon was bluffing. Napoleon had no
intention of lifting restrictions on the
Americans and was lying to get America
to embargo Britain anyway. John Quincy
Adams called it a deception so blatant
it would give sight to the blind. When
Britain realized France wasn't going to
budge, it decided not to bother either.
The US had tried every mode of coercion
short of war, as one congressman put it,
to get Britain to stop its attacks on
American trade. When all other methods
had failed, what option did they have
but war? This was the argument James
Madison made when he spoke before
Congress on June 1st, 1812.
No nation could endure these attacks on
its sailors and ships without doing
anything about it. The official
declaration of war was signed on June
18th. Unknown to the Americans, Britain
had in fact revoked the orders and
council 2 days before on June 16th.
News took weeks to travel between London
and Washington, though, and the two
nations found themselves at war just as
one of the chief causes of that war was
being repealed. With a vote of 79 to 49
in the House and 19-13 in the Senate, it
was the closest war vote in US history.
It was a clear partisan split with the
Republicans rallying to war and the
Federalists calling for peace.
Republicans like Jefferson and Madison
had always favored France while the
Federalists had always inclined towards
Britain. For many Republicans,
federalist reluctance to go to war
hinted at their true desire to overthrow
the republic and restore the British
monarchy. This certainly wasn't true,
but the idea that the Americans were
fighting to protect the ideas of
democracy and freedom from British
tyranny was a potent one. The strange
part was the regional differences in
support for the war.
The war was supposedly fought over
Britain's interruptions of maritime
trade and the impressment of sailors,
but New England, which suffered most
from these, voted mostly against the war
in Congress and was reluctant to assist
the war effort.
Meanwhile, southern and western states
with no naval trade were overwhelmingly
in favor of it.
This shows that the real causes of the
war were a lot more complex. Western
support for the war probably came from a
desire to acquire land in Canada from
the British and to punish the British
for their support of Indian groups in
the Northwest such as Tekkums
Confederacy who were fighting against
American settlers.
There was also an age split with old
guard congressmen generally going
against the war while younger members
like JC Calhoun of South Carolina and
Henry Clay of Kentucky were more
enthusiastic.
This younger generation had not fought
in the revolution and seemed to want
their own chance at glory against the
British. In Calhoun's own words, they
wanted to prove that we have not only
inherited the liberty which our fathers
gave us, but also the will and power to
maintain it. But America was in no shape
for a war. The US Army had less than
7,000 troops. And even when Congress
authorized the recruitment of another
25,000 of them, they struggled to find
the recruits. By November 1812, they
hadn't raised 10,000 new volunteers and
could barely afford to give them
uniforms. Aside from regular troops, the
US would have to rely on volunteers
serving for a term of one year and the
state militias, even though they weren't
supposed to serve outside of their own
state. The naval situation was even
worse. There was a great concern among
Republicans that a navy would pose a
threat to freedom and peaceime and
create a naval elite class who might
dominate the state. In January 1812,
Congress voted against expanding the
navy even as tensions with Britain were
climbing. As a result, America entered
the war with just 17 warships. only
seven of them frigots and none were
ships of the line that dominated naval
warfare of the age. Britain's North
America fleet at the outbreak of the war
was just one ship of the line and nine
frigots. Barely a fraction of the Royal
Navy's global strength, but still enough
to crush the Americans in a straight
fight. To top it all off, Madison and
the Republicans resisted raising taxes
as long as possible until March 1812, as
the abolition of the Bank of the United
States in 1811 made it difficult for the
US to borrow money if it needed it. The
odds were clearly stacked against
America on paper. In practice, the
Americans hoped that strong leadership
and good old American spirit would see
them through while Britain was
distracted by Napoleon.
It was decided that invading Canada
would be the best option. The Americans
believed the Canadians were just waiting
for the chance to rise up against the
British and they'd barely have to fire a
shot in order to kick the British out.
The campaign, as the retired Thomas
Jefferson wrote, would be a mere matter
of marching. The invasion of Canada
would be a threepronged affair. One
invasion would proceed from Michigan
under General William Hull. A second
force under General Steven von Renelier
would cross the Niagara River. The third
under General Henry Dearbornne would
march from Albany, New York, and aim for
Montreal.
The plan was immediately beset with
problems. Hull dithered and delayed the
attack on the British Fort Malden on the
Canadian Michigan border.
Ohio's militia men refused to cross the
border and join any attack he made.
Hull was also paranoid of British
reinforcements sneaking up on him and
troubled by endless rumors of Indian
attacks behind his lines.
Only on July 12th did he order his men
into Canadian territory, expecting, like
Jefferson did, that the Canadians would
rally to his call and fight the British.
Hull was completely disappointed and
received no volunteers. On July 16th,
his forces encountered a British
scouting party, marking the first proper
engagement and casualties of the war. 3
weeks later, on August 6th, he finally
began his actual attack on Fort Malden.
But when news reached him of an Indian
ambush upon US troops at Maguaga, he
feared he would be outflanked and
ordered a full retreat back to Detroit.
The entire campaign had failed to
achieve anything. The British almost
couldn't believe their luck. They
immediately went on the offensive,
intentionally spreading false
information about the number of Indian
allies they were bringing with them to
incite fear and headed straight for
Detroit. Hull's resolve collapsed
completely when British troops appeared
outside the walls of Detroit on August
16th. He surrendered without firing a
shot and all of Michigan was handed over
to the British. Hull was allowed to
return home where his actions got him
court marshaled and sentenced to death.
Madison stepped in at the last minute to
spare him execution in light of his
service in the Revolutionary War, but he
spent the rest of his life in disgrace.
Over in New England, General Dearborn
couldn't get New England to offer up the
troops he needed for his campaign. New
England wasn't eager for a war in the
first place, and the state militias
weren't supposed to serve outside their
state, no matter what Madison or
Dearbornne's orders demanded.
Frustrated with the delay, Steven von
Renelier took his 4,000 regular troops
across the Niagara River in October
1812.
Von Renelier's men took the British by
surprise at Queenston and gained the
upper hand in the battle at first. To
seal the victory though, they needed
reinforcements and the only troops that
were to hand were the New York militia.
The militia refused orders to cross the
border and von Renelier's unsupported
men were soon overwhelmed by British and
Canadian troops. They retreated back
across the Niagara River with 100 dead
and nothing to show for it. Only in
November did General Dearborn finally
assemble enough men for the attack
towards Montreal. Dearbornne set out
from Albany with 6,800
men, which unfortunately included many
state militia men. As soon as they got
to the Canadian border, many of the
militia men decided they didn't want to
go into Canada after all. 2,000 of them
left his army, and Dearborn's campaign
was over before it began. He fought a
single battle at the LL mills on
November 20th, losing five men to a
British and Indian force about 120th the
size of his own before giving up and
turning back. One contemporary described
the whole campaign as a miscarriage
without even the heroism of a disaster.
Surprisingly, the only part of the war
in 1812 that didn't go terribly for the
US was at sea. America didn't have any
ships of the line, but it did have some
wellarmored frigots that could stand up
to any of those in the Royal Navy. With
so few British ships spread out across
North America, the US knew the only hope
of victory was luring these British
ships into one-on-one engagements where
America actually stood a chance.
On August 19th, Captain Isaac Hall of
the Frigot USS Constitution and the
nephew of the disgraced William Hall did
exactly that,
catching and sinking the HMS Guerier in
open battle.
The Constitution was so wellarmored that
British cannonballs would bounce right
off the hull, earning her the nickname
Old Iron Sides.
The sinking of one ship had little
practical effect, but Old Ironside's
victory was the only real good news of
the war so far. Seeing this success,
Madison ordered his ships to be split
into three squadrons to hunt down what
British ships they could. The strategy
worked and several British ships were
sunk. In October, the Americans even
managed to capture the HMS Macedonian
and sail it back to port as a war prize.
The first time the US had ever done such
a thing. By the end of the year, the
tiny American Navy had won more
individual engagements against the
British than France's navy had done in
the last 20 years of conflict. On top of
this, privateeers, basically legally
sanctioned pirates, seized 450 British
trading vessels in 1812, inflicting a
serious blow on Britain's American
trade.
America's naval victories had little
strategic value, but they were badly
needed for American morale after the
failures in Canada. They were also
enough to maintain confidence in
Madison's leadership, allowing him to
win re-election in November 1812.
However, these small victories could not
disguise the truth. America had lost
Michigan and hundreds of troops against
an enemy with more troops and ships than
they could hope to match.
The War of 1812 was only just beginning,
but all signs pointed towards disaster
for the United States. 1812 had been a
miserable year for the United States,
save for a few minor naval victories.
They had suffered nothing but defeat and
embarrassment. Suddenly, declaring war
on the world's most powerful empire with
only a few thousand men and a handful of
ships to hand seemed like a mistake.
Britain had more men, more ships, and
more resources, and the will to use them
to crush their former colonies. This was
no longer a war about trade disputes,
but a struggle for the survival of the
American nation itself.
The first order of business was to
overhaul the leadership. Out went
William Eustace as Secretary of War and
in came John Armstrong who'd served
under Washington and had been one of the
leaders in the famous 1783 Newberg
mutiny. Secretary of the Navy Paul
Hamilton was also replaced by William
Jones, another veteran of the
revolution. Congress then voted for
another 20,000 regular troops, six
frigots, and four ships of the line. On
the front lines, William Hull's vacant
command was filled by William Henry
Harrison. Since Tecumsa's Indians had
played such a big role in British
victories in the north, Harrison's
appointment had made sense. Back in
1811, he'd led the American forces to
victory over Tcumsa's Confederacy at the
Battle of Typicanu. And it was hoped
that he could repeat that same success
again. America's primary goals in 1813
was to break British control over
Michigan and make inroads along the
Niagara River. In doing so, they would
seize control of the Great Lakes region.
Harrison took the initiative in Michigan
while General Henry Dearbornne continued
to command in the Northeast. Dearbornne
set York, modern-day Toronto, as his
initial target. As the capital of
British Canada, it was a valuable and
vulnerable settlement and would make for
an inspiring victory for the men. In
April 1813, they struck out across Lake
Ontario and on the 27th attacked and
captured York. The Americans stripped
the city of any supplies they could find
before setting it ablaze. The burning of
their capital was an insult that the
British and Canadians would not forget.
Then in May, Dearbornne's infantry
coordinated with the US Navy in one of
the first successful amphibious assaults
in American history to capture Fort
George on the Niagara River. While most
of the British troops escaped the
battle, the capture of the fort was
another welcome victory.
In the west, Harrison's campaign got off
to a poor start. He lost hundreds of men
at the Battle of Raisin River in January
1813.
Stories of the brutal treatment
inflicted by Indian warriors on captured
American troops after the battle caused
a popular scandal in the press, but also
seemed to harden American resolve
against their enemy. Once again,
American ships proved victorious where
infantry had failed. On September 10th,
1813, a nine vessel fleet led by Oliver
Perry sailed into Lake Erie and defeated
the British fleet stationed there. In
doing so, he destroyed Britain's vital
supply lines into Michigan. In one
afternoon's battle, Perry made Britain's
control of the entire peninsula
untenable, and they called a full
retreat.
General Harrison aggressively pursued
the retreating British and their Indian
allies back into Canada. On October 5th,
his troops caught up with them at
Moravian Town on the Tames. With 3,000
Americans against 430 British and 600
Indians, the American victory was a
clear one. The British commander was
captured and the Shauny Indian leader
Tkumsa was killed which caused the
collapse of the Indian Confederacy he
built. It was America's greatest victory
of the war so far. But this winning
streak didn't last. The front stabilized
in the second half of 1813 until British
counterattacks retook Fort George and
pushed the Americans back across the
Niagara River. General Dearbornne was
finally relieved of his command by the
end of the year. At sea, America's early
victories were made a thing of the past
as the Royal Navy dispatched more ships
to assert control of the waves. They
enforced a blockade along most of the
Atlantic coast and denied American
vessels freedom of movement. By the end
of the year, virtually all American
maritime warships had been sunk or
confined to port for their own
protection. Trade had cratered from
around $100 million annually in 1807 to
just 27 million in 1813 and 7 million in
1814.
Government revenue collapsed too from 13
million in 1811 to 6 million in 1815.
Meanwhile, as America was pushing to
resolve fighting in the north, it soon
found itself facing new problems in the
south. Among the Creek Indians, an
anti-American faction inspired by
Tecumpsa, known as the Red Sticks,
called their fellow Creek, to attack the
Americans in the south while they were
distracted by the war. Britain secretly
supported these red sticks who in August
of 1813 overran and killed US troops at
Fort Mims in Arkansas. With most troops
tied up in the north, it fell to the
Tennessee militia under Major General
Andrew Jackson to respond.
The death of Tkumsa in October 1813 did
nothing to deter the Red Sticks, who
continued to raid American settlements
and forts around their territory. But
Jackson's militia men weren't as
squeamish about crossing state lines as
New England's were. And so they arrived
at Horseshoe Bend along the Talapusa
River on March 27th, 1814 to face down
the Creek warriors. The resulting battle
was a tragedy for the Creek. Of the
1,000 Creek warriors on the field, only
200 survived the battle. Jackson's
victory virtually ended creek resistance
to the United States and dealt a fatal
blow to British plans to open a new
front in the South. To make matters
worse for the Americans, however,
Napoleon surrendered on March 31st,
1814.
This allowed Britain to pivot its full
attention to America. An army of 15,000
battleh hardened veterans was shipped
over to Canada with a bold plan. The
British would invade New England over
Lake Champlain where they expected
sympathetic Federalists to flock to
their banner. At the same time, the
Royal Navy would bombard the coast from
Charleston to Chesapeake Bay. Another
invasion force under General Edward
Packenham would land on the Gulf Coast
and link up with Britain's Creek Indian
allies to attack New Orleans, unaware of
the Creek defeat at Horseshoe Bend.
However, the most important angle of
attack would come in the Chesapeake Bay,
where 4,000 men and two dozen warships
were assembled to strike at one
particular target, Washington, DC. On
August 24th, 4,000 British troops made
landfall at Bladensburg, a few miles
north of Washington, DC, where they
quickly overwhelmed the weak local
defenders. Washington had no effective
defenses and no plan to repel the
British. President Madison was outside
the capital meeting with army leaders,
but others, including the first lady,
members of his cabinet, and many
congressmen were still in the capital
when the British appeared on the
horizon.
It was a frantic dash to escape the
city. First Lady Dolly Madison barely
had time to gather some of her
belongings and a portrait of George
Washington before she fled the White
House. Anything that couldn't be carried
was left behind, including the contents
of the US Treasury and the Library of
Congress. British troops marched into
Washington DC that evening with only a
handful of American soldiers trying to
defend it. British Rear Admiral George
Cochburn and General Robert Ross dined
at the president's table that evening,
and when they were done, they decided to
repay the Americans for what they' done
to York the previous year. The White
House, the Capitol building, the
Treasury, and several other prominent
public buildings were set ablaze. The
fires lighting up the night for miles
around.
With its capital in ashes, and yet
another British army under Canadian
Governor General George Po crossing into
New York, the United States was facing
the biggest military crisis since its
inception. The grand American experiment
hung on by a thread. And it seems the
British were about to cut it off for
good.
Late 1814,
Washington DC is in ashes. Multiple
British armies are on US soil. Having
vanquished Napoleon, the full might of a
battleh hardened British Empire is now
arrayed against the United States of
America. The final act of the War of
1812 was shaping up to be a devastating
end for the United States.
In late August, Governor General George
Po of Canada had crossed into New York
with a fresh army. The British had hoped
that the sympathetic Federalists of New
England might flock to join them, just
as America had hoped the Canadians would
turn on the British back in 1812. The
British were mistaken, too, and didn't
receive the sudden surge of local
support they had hoped for. But even if
they had, it wouldn't have mattered. The
Royal Navy ruled the seas, but its
dominion over Lake Champlain, which was
necessary to maintain supply lines for
PO's army, was not so strong. On
September 11th, 1814, a British naval
contingent attacks the 14 American
vessels defending Platsburg on Lake
Champlain. Expecting an easy victory,
the Americans had anchored themselves
near the shore and forced the British to
come at them on their own terms. The
waiting American guns tore the British
fleet to pieces, killing hundreds of
sailors, including the fleet's captain,
George Downey, and forcing the British
ships to surrender. The Battle of
Platsburg destroyed the supply lines PO
needed for his invasion, and he was
forced to retreat back to Canada.
Meanwhile, after burning Washington, the
British marched onwards to Baltimore. On
September 12th, they forced a landing at
North Point near the city and routed the
American defenders, but at the cost of
General Robert Ross's life. The loss of
one of their key commanders did not slow
them down, though, as British troops
advanced upon Baltimore itself, where
the Americans had holed up inside Fort
Mckenry. Early in the morning of
September 13th, the Royal Navy opened
fire on Fort Mckenry. Over the next 24
hours, they hurled 1,500 shells at it,
battering its defenders with enough
firepower to level a city. It was almost
a miracle that the walls held and the
defenders only suffered light
casualties. As the smoke cleared and the
guns fell silent on September 14th, the
American flag still waved defiantly
above the fort. The sight of that star
spangled banner inspired one eyewitness
named Francis Scott Keyi to write a poem
named after that flag which became the
US national anthem. Britain's failure to
break Fort McHenry halted their offense
in its tracks. On September 15th, they
were forced to retreat, ending their
campaign in Virginia. In the space of 4
days, America had turned back both of
Britain's assaults in the Northeast.
America's victory at the Battle of
Baltimore was a relief, but America was
still in a dire state. Morale was low.
US troops had a desertion rate of 12%
and the Secretary of War John Armstrong
had to resign 2 weeks later because
confidence in his leadership had totally
collapsed. On top of that, in the words
of Treasury Secretary George Campbell,
the nation's finances had suffered every
kind of embarrassment. He too resigned
on October 1814, unable to scrape
together the $50 million needed to cover
the country's expenses. As a result, the
US defaulted on its debts for the first
and only time in its history that
November.
Since we started this channel, we have
been obsessed with historical maps.
Since some of you might like maps as
well, we created a few products for you.
Highresolution downloads and museum
quality prints. Go to knowledigia.co and
have a look. If you want to own one, use
my code in the description below. Now,
back to the video.
For the Republicans, it was a nightmare
so awful that they voted to raise taxes.
For the Federalists, it was practically
free ammunition. The Republicans have
ruined the country by driving us into a
war we cannot win was an easy pitch to
make. Their despair over the state of
the war was so intense that in December,
representatives of the Federalists in
New England met at Hartford for a
landmark conference with a harshly
condemned conduct of the war and
Madison's administration. They argued
that the failures spoke to deeper
structural problems in the US government
and proposed a sweeping set of
amendments that would be the most
radical shakeup in the US government
since the constitution had been
ratified. They called for the
elimination of the three-fifths clause,
which gave more representation to slave
states who had voted for the war, wanted
to ban the admission of new states,
eliminate government embargo power,
require a supermajority for war
declarations, and limit presidents to a
single term. The declaration was signed
and sent to Washington in January 1815.
However, unknown to the Federalists,
events had been transpiring that would
radically change things by the time that
declaration arrived.
While the war had been raging, Madison
had always been searching for a peaceful
solution. In March 1813, Russia had
offered to mediate negotiations between
America and Britain. The US ambassador
to Russia, future President John Quincy
Adams, was happy to accept such a
proposal, but Britain declined. They
didn't need Russia getting involved.
They did, however, agree to negotiate in
Belgium. Madison ordered Adams to meet
with the British again in August 1814
and sent over several other delegates,
including Henry Clay of Kentucky and
Jonathan Russell of Rhode Island to
support him. The negotiations spanned
four long months, but the American
delegation was probably one of the best
diplomatic teams ever assembled.
Intelligent, persuasive, and impossible
to intimidate, they were a league apart
from the British negotiating team, none
of whom were particularly noteworthy or
accomplished. Since every good diplomat
was too busy dealing with the fallout of
the Napoleonic Wars to bother with the
American sideshow,
Britain's initial demands were harsh. A
permanent Indian reservation in the
Northwest, American demilitarization in
the Great Lakes, handing Maine to the
British and giving them trade privileges
in the Mississippi. The British were
surprised when the Americans turned them
down. The British then tried to delay
until word of a clear British victory
could cow the Americans into submission,
but that failed too. The Americans were
completely unfased by news of Washington
DC being burned down. If anything, the
opposite happened. News of American
victories at Platsburg and Baltimore
shook British confidence instead.
Eventually, the British decided they
were quote not likely to attain any
glory or renown at all, commensurate to
the inconvenience it will occasion from
extending the war in America. On
Christmas Eve 1814, the two teams signed
the Treaty of Gent, agreeing to make
peace and restore all territory to what
it had been before the war began. There
wasn't even an acknowledgement of the
trade disputes or impressment that had
triggered the war. Both sides just
wanted it over with. Alas, news traveled
slowly across the Atlantic. And there
was a third complication to the
situation to consider Andrew Jackson.
In April 1814, fresh British troops had
arrived on the Gulf Coast, ready to
attack the US on another front. General
Edward Pachinham landed expecting to
meet with his Red Stick Indian allies
only to learn about their crushing
defeat at Horseshoe Bend weeks earlier.
There weren't enough Indians left to
support their planned attacks. So, the
British and Indians decided to harass
American positions instead while waiting
for reinforcements. Thanks to the war in
Europe, Spain and Britain were cautious
allies. So, Spain allowed Britain to
operate out of Pensacola in Spanish
Florida. Andrew Jackson wasn't going to
let that stand. On November 7th, 1814,
he stormed across the border with 4,000
men and attacked Pensacola. It was the
first time the US had invaded Spanish
territory. The Spanish surrendered the
city after a short fight since they
weren't keen on the British being in the
city either, while the British and
Indians were forced to withdraw but
suffered minimal casualties. Jackson's
attack on Pensacola re-energized that
theater of the war in its 11th hour.
After withdrawing from Spanish Florida,
Jackson took his men back to New Orleans
where he knew the British would strike
next. Admiral Alexander Cochran and
General Pachenham were indeed preparing
an invasion at the mouth of the
Mississippi. Even as negotiators in
Belgium were ironing out peace terms. On
January 8th, 1815, as those peace terms
were sailing across the Atlantic,
Paganim's forces landed on the shoreline
just outside New Orleans. Jackson had
spent the last two months fortifying the
city for an assault. And when the 8,000
British troops appeared outside the
walls, they found out how well he'd
prepared for them. Casualties were high
and very lopsided. 300 British soldiers,
including General Pachinam, were killed.
1,200 were injured and 500 were
captured. Before the sun had even set,
the British had retreated. The Americans
lost just 12 men.
The Battle of New Orleans was the most
decisive victory of the entire war, and
Andrew Jackson became the greatest
American military hero of his day. News
of the victory arrived in Washington
some days later and quickly spread
across the US to much celebration. The
timing couldn't have been better. The
New Orleans news dropped days before the
New England Federalists published their
Hartford Declaration condemning the war
and making demands to reform the
government. The Federalist statement
couldn't have had a more hostile
audience. The declaration was seen as
spiteful, out of touch, and even
traitorous and damaged the Federalist
Party's reputation so badly that it
never recovered. The party of Washington
and Hamilton would limp on for a few
more years before vanishing into
history.
It also preceded the news of the Treaty
of Gent, which reached Washington on
February 13th, 1815.
Many Americans falsely believed that
America had compelled the British to
peace after New Orleans, and were
totally unaware of the negotiations that
had actually led to the treaty. No one
was eager to correct the
misunderstanding, least of all President
Madison or the Republicans, who declared
it a tremendous victory for the United
States. While it raged, the War of 1812
was probably the most unpopular American
war until Vietnam. But despite a
generally poor military performance, a
ruined economy, and a burned capital,
the United States was able to spin the
War of 1812 into a victory in its final
weeks. Jackson's success at New Orleans
washed away the failures and allowed
Madison to emerge from the war, singing
a song of victory and patriotism.
The War of 1812 produced no lasting
territorial changes. It did not alter
the American government or change how
wars were fought. It claimed around
2,000 American lives in combat, plus
several thousand to disease and other
causes. It also left its mark in small
ways. The legend of old iron sides, the
reputation of Andrew Jackson, the
collapse of the Federalist Party, and
the creation of the Star Spangled
Banner, to name a few. It certainly
mattered to Indians like the Creek and
the Shaune who suffered historic defeats
at American hands during the conflict.
Canada too was forever changed with
Canadian victories such as Queenston
Heights in 1812 being formative moments
for Canadian nationalism where they
stopped being merely British or French
colonists and started to see themselves
as distinctly Canadian. Similarly, this
was the war's lasting legacy in America
as well. It was the first trial by fire
of America's government and people
against an enemy who could equal them.
Shared hardship created a shared
identity. It built a sense of national
unity and pride that long outlasted the
war. In the words of one congressman,
the people were now more American. They
feel and act more as a nation. So while
the War of 1812 is easily forgotten
today, it played a vital role in making
the United States what it is. America
would fight many larger wars with higher
stakes and greater casualties. But the
idea of the United States and the anthem
that embodies that idea will always owe
a special debt to this overlooked
conflict.
If you'd like to help us keep creating
and get early access to our videos,
behindthe-scenes content, and other
perks, consider becoming a member right
here on YouTube or joining us on
Patreon. Every bit of support helps. And
as always, thank you so much for
watching.